# title: Moby Dick
# chapter: 101
# annotator: Vincent Labatut
# guidelines-version: 1.0.0
# last-updated: 13-07-2024
# comment: 

Ere O
the O
English B-GRP
ship O
fades O
from O
sight O
, O
be O
it O
set O
down O
here O
, O
that O
she O
hailed O
from O
London B-LOC
, O
and O
was O
named O
after O
the O
late O
Samuel B-CHR
Enderby I-CHR
, O
merchant O
of O
that O
city O
, O
the O
original O
of O
the O
famous O
whaling O
house O
of O
Enderby B-ORG
& I-ORG
Sons I-ORG
; O
a O
house O
which O
in O
my O
poor O
whaleman O
’ O
s O
opinion O
, O
comes O
not O
far O
behind O
the O
united O
royal O
houses O
of O
the O
Tudors B-GRP
and O
Bourbons B-GRP
, O
in O
point O
of O
real O
historical O
interest O
. O
How O
long O
, O
prior O
to O
the O
year O
of O
our O
Lord O
1775 O
, O
this O
great O
whaling O
house O
was O
in O
existence O
, O
my O
numerous O
fish-documents O
do O
not O
make O
plain O
; O
but O
in O
that O
year O
( O
1775 O
) O
it O
fitted O
out O
the O
first O
English B-GRP
ships O
that O
ever O
regularly O
hunted O
the O
Sperm O
Whale O
; O
though O
for O
some O
score O
of O
years O
previous O
( O
ever O
since O
1726 O
) O
our O
valiant O
Coffins B-GRP
and O
Maceys B-GRP
of O
Nantucket B-LOC
and O
the O
Vineyard B-LOC
had O
in O
large O
fleets O
pursued O
that O
Leviathan B-CHR
, O
but O
only O
in O
the O
North O
and O
South B-LOC
Atlantic I-LOC
: O
not O
elsewhere O
. O
Be O
it O
distinctly O
recorded O
here O
, O
that O
the O
Nantucketers B-GRP
were O
the O
first O
among O
mankind O
to O
harpoon O
with O
civilized O
steel O
the O
great O
Sperm O
Whale O
; O
and O
that O
for O
half O
a O
century O
they O
were O
the O
only O
people O
of O
the O
whole O
globe O
who O
so O
harpooned O
him O
. O
In O
1778 O
, O
a O
fine O
ship O
, O
the O
Amelia B-MSC
, O
fitted O
out O
for O
the O
express O
purpose O
, O
and O
at O
the O
sole O
charge O
of O
the O
vigorous O
Enderbys B-GRP
, O
boldly O
rounded O
Cape B-LOC
Horn I-LOC
, O
and O
was O
the O
first O
among O
the O
nations O
to O
lower O
a O
whale-boat O
of O
any O
sort O
in O
the O
great O
South B-LOC
Sea I-LOC
. O
The O
voyage O
was O
a O
skilful O
and O
lucky O
one O
; O
and O
returning O
to O
her O
berth O
with O
her O
hold O
full O
of O
the O
precious O
sperm O
, O
the O
Amelia B-MSC
’ O
s O
example O
was O
soon O
followed O
by O
other O
ships O
, O
English B-GRP
and O
American B-GRP
, O
and O
thus O
the O
vast O
Sperm O
Whale O
grounds O
of O
the O
Pacific B-LOC
were O
thrown O
open O
. O
But O
not O
content O
with O
this O
good O
deed O
, O
the O
indefatigable O
house O
again O
bestirred O
itself O
: O
Samuel B-CHR
and O
all O
his O
Sons—how O
many O
, O
their O
mother O
only O
knows—and O
under O
their O
immediate O
auspices O
, O
and O
partly O
, O
I O
think O
, O
at O
their O
expense O
, O
the O
British B-GRP
government O
was O
induced O
to O
send O
the O
sloop-of-war O
Rattler B-MSC
on O
a O
whaling O
voyage O
of O
discovery O
into O
the O
South B-LOC
Sea I-LOC
. O
Commanded O
by O
a O
naval O
Post-Captain O
, O
the O
Rattler B-MSC
made O
a O
rattling O
voyage O
of O
it O
, O
and O
did O
some O
service O
; O
how O
much O
does O
not O
appear O
. O
But O
this O
is O
not O
all O
. O
In O
1819 O
, O
the O
same O
house O
fitted O
out O
a O
discovery O
whale O
ship O
of O
their O
own O
, O
to O
go O
on O
a O
tasting O
cruise O
to O
the O
remote O
waters O
of O
Japan B-LOC
. O
That O
ship—well O
called O
the O
“ O
Syren B-MSC
” O
—made O
a O
noble O
experimental O
cruise O
; O
and O
it O
was O
thus O
that O
the O
great O
Japanese O
Whaling O
Ground O
first O
became O
generally O
known O
. O
The O
Syren B-MSC
in O
this O
famous O
voyage O
was O
commanded O
by O
a O
Captain B-CHR
Coffin I-CHR
, O
a O
Nantucketer B-GRP
. O
All O
honor O
to O
the O
Enderbies B-GRP
, O
therefore O
, O
whose O
house O
, O
I O
think O
, O
exists O
to O
the O
present O
day O
; O
though O
doubtless O
the O
original O
Samuel B-CHR
must O
long O
ago O
have O
slipped O
his O
cable O
for O
the O
great O
South B-LOC
Sea I-LOC
of O
the O
other O
world O
. O
The O
ship O
named O
after O
him O
was O
worthy O
of O
the O
honor O
, O
being O
a O
very O
fast O
sailer O
and O
a O
noble O
craft O
every O
way O
. O
I O
boarded O
her O
once O
at O
midnight O
somewhere O
off O
the O
Patagonian B-GRP
coast O
, O
and O
drank O
good O
flip O
down O
in O
the O
forecastle O
. O
It O
was O
a O
fine O
gam O
we O
had O
, O
and O
they O
were O
all O
trumps—every O
soul O
on O
board O
. O
A O
short O
life O
to O
them O
, O
and O
a O
jolly O
death O
. O
And O
that O
fine O
gam O
I O
had—long O
, O
very O
long O
after O
old O
Ahab B-CHR
touched O
her O
planks O
with O
his O
ivory O
heel—it O
minds O
me O
of O
the O
noble O
, O
solid O
, O
Saxon B-GRP
hospitality O
of O
that O
ship O
; O
and O
may O
my O
parson O
forget O
me O
, O
and O
the O
devil O
remember O
me O
, O
if O
I O
ever O
lose O
sight O
of O
it O
. O
Flip O
? O
Did O
I O
say O
we O
had O
flip O
? O
Yes O
, O
and O
we O
flipped O
it O
at O
the O
rate O
of O
ten O
gallons O
the O
hour O
; O
and O
when O
the O
squall O
came O
( O
for O
it O
’ O
s O
squally O
off O
there O
by O
Patagonia B-LOC
) O
, O
and O
all O
hands—visitors O
and O
all—were O
called O
to O
reef O
topsails O
, O
we O
were O
so O
top-heavy O
that O
we O
had O
to O
swing O
each O
other O
aloft O
in O
bowlines O
; O
and O
we O
ignorantly O
furled O
the O
skirts O
of O
our O
jackets O
into O
the O
sails O
, O
so O
that O
we O
hung O
there O
, O
reefed O
fast O
in O
the O
howling O
gale O
, O
a O
warning O
example O
to O
all O
drunken O
tars O
. O
However O
, O
the O
masts O
did O
not O
go O
overboard O
; O
and O
by O
and O
by O
we O
scrambled O
down O
, O
so O
sober O
, O
that O
we O
had O
to O
pass O
the O
flip O
again O
, O
though O
the O
savage O
salt O
spray O
bursting O
down O
the O
forecastle O
scuttle O
, O
rather O
too O
much O
diluted O
and O
pickled O
it O
to O
my O
taste O
. O
The O
beef O
was O
fine—tough O
, O
but O
with O
body O
in O
it O
. O
They O
said O
it O
was O
bull-beef O
; O
others O
, O
that O
it O
was O
dromedary O
beef O
; O
but O
I O
do O
not O
know O
, O
for O
certain O
, O
how O
that O
was O
. O
They O
had O
dumplings O
too O
; O
small O
, O
but O
substantial O
, O
symmetrically O
globular O
, O
and O
indestructible O
dumplings O
. O
I O
fancied O
that O
you O
could O
feel O
them O
, O
and O
roll O
them O
about O
in O
you O
after O
they O
were O
swallowed O
. O
If O
you O
stooped O
over O
too O
far O
forward O
, O
you O
risked O
their O
pitching O
out O
of O
you O
like O
billiard-balls O
. O
The O
bread—but O
that O
couldn O
’ O
t O
be O
helped O
; O
besides O
, O
it O
was O
an O
anti-scorbutic O
; O
in O
short O
, O
the O
bread O
contained O
the O
only O
fresh O
fare O
they O
had O
. O
But O
the O
forecastle O
was O
not O
very O
light O
, O
and O
it O
was O
very O
easy O
to O
step O
over O
into O
a O
dark O
corner O
when O
you O
ate O
it O
. O
But O
all O
in O
all O
, O
taking O
her O
from O
truck O
to O
helm O
, O
considering O
the O
dimensions O
of O
the O
cook O
’ O
s O
boilers O
, O
including O
his O
own O
live O
parchment O
boilers O
; O
fore O
and O
aft O
, O
I O
say O
, O
the O
Samuel B-MSC
Enderby I-MSC
was O
a O
jolly O
ship O
; O
of O
good O
fare O
and O
plenty O
; O
fine O
flip O
and O
strong O
; O
crack O
fellows O
all O
, O
and O
capital O
from O
boot O
heels O
to O
hat-band O
. O
But O
why O
was O
it O
, O
think O
ye O
, O
that O
the O
Samuel B-MSC
Enderby I-MSC
, O
and O
some O
other O
English B-GRP
whalers O
I O
know O
of—not O
all O
though—were O
such O
famous O
, O
hospitable O
ships O
; O
that O
passed O
round O
the O
beef O
, O
and O
the O
bread O
, O
and O
the O
can O
, O
and O
the O
joke O
; O
and O
were O
not O
soon O
weary O
of O
eating O
, O
and O
drinking O
, O
and O
laughing O
? O
I O
will O
tell O
you O
. O
The O
abounding O
good O
cheer O
of O
these O
English B-GRP
whalers O
is O
matter O
for O
historical O
research O
. O
Nor O
have O
I O
been O
at O
all O
sparing O
of O
historical O
whale O
research O
, O
when O
it O
has O
seemed O
needed O
. O
The O
English B-GRP
were O
preceded O
in O
the O
whale O
fishery O
by O
the O
Hollanders B-GRP
, O
Zealanders B-GRP
, O
and O
Danes B-GRP
; O
from O
whom O
they O
derived O
many O
terms O
still O
extant O
in O
the O
fishery O
; O
and O
what O
is O
yet O
more O
, O
their O
fat O
old O
fashions O
, O
touching O
plenty O
to O
eat O
and O
drink O
. O
For O
, O
as O
a O
general O
thing O
, O
the O
English B-GRP
merchant-ship O
scrimps O
her O
crew O
; O
but O
not O
so O
the O
English B-GRP
whaler O
. O
Hence O
, O
in O
the O
English B-GRP
, O
this O
thing O
of O
whaling O
good O
cheer O
is O
not O
normal O
and O
natural O
, O
but O
incidental O
and O
particular O
; O
and O
, O
therefore O
, O
must O
have O
some O
special O
origin O
, O
which O
is O
here O
pointed O
out O
, O
and O
will O
be O
still O
further O
elucidated O
. O
During O
my O
researches O
in O
the O
Leviathanic O
histories O
, O
I O
stumbled O
upon O
an O
ancient O
Dutch B-GRP
volume O
, O
which O
, O
by O
the O
musty O
whaling O
smell O
of O
it O
, O
I O
knew O
must O
be O
about O
whalers O
. O
The O
title O
was O
, O
“ O
Dan B-MSC
Coopman I-MSC
, O
” O
wherefore O
I O
concluded O
that O
this O
must O
be O
the O
invaluable O
memoirs O
of O
some O
Amsterdam B-LOC
cooper O
in O
the O
fishery O
, O
as O
every O
whale O
ship O
must O
carry O
its O
cooper O
. O
I O
was O
reinforced O
in O
this O
opinion O
by O
seeing O
that O
it O
was O
the O
production O
of O
one O
“ O
Fitz B-CHR
Swackhammer I-CHR
. O
” O
But O
my O
friend O
Dr. B-CHR
Snodhead I-CHR
, O
a O
very O
learned O
man O
, O
professor O
of O
Low B-MSC
Dutch I-MSC
and O
High B-MSC
German I-MSC
in O
the O
college O
of O
Santa B-LOC
Claus I-LOC
and O
St. B-LOC
Pott I-LOC
’ O
s O
, O
to O
whom O
I O
handed O
the O
work O
for O
translation O
, O
giving O
him O
a O
box O
of O
sperm O
candles O
for O
his O
trouble—this O
same O
Dr. B-CHR
Snodhead I-CHR
, O
so O
soon O
as O
he O
spied O
the O
book O
, O
assured O
me O
that O
“ O
Dan B-MSC
Coopman I-MSC
” O
did O
not O
mean O
“ O
The O
Cooper O
, O
” O
but O
“ O
The O
Merchant. O
” O
In O
short O
, O
this O
ancient O
and O
learned O
Low B-MSC
Dutch I-MSC
book O
treated O
of O
the O
commerce O
of O
Holland B-LOC
; O
and O
, O
among O
other O
subjects O
, O
contained O
a O
very O
interesting O
account O
of O
its O
whale O
fishery O
. O
And O
in O
this O
chapter O
it O
was O
, O
headed O
, O
“ O
Smeer O
, O
” O
or O
“ O
Fat O
, O
” O
that O
I O
found O
a O
long O
detailed O
list O
of O
the O
outfits O
for O
the O
larders O
and O
cellars O
of O
180 O
sail O
of O
Dutch B-GRP
whalemen O
; O
from O
which O
list O
, O
as O
translated O
by O
Dr. B-CHR
Snodhead I-CHR
, O
I O
transcribe O
the O
following O
: O
400,000 O
lbs O
. O
of O
beef O
. O
60,000 O
lbs O
. O
Friesland B-GRP
pork O
. O
150,000 O
lbs O
. O
of O
stock O
fish O
. O
550,000 O
lbs O
. O
of O
biscuit O
. O
72,000 O
lbs O
. O
of O
soft O
bread O
. O
2,800 O
firkins O
of O
butter O
. O
20,000 O
lbs O
. O
Texel B-ORG
& I-ORG
Leyden I-ORG
cheese O
. O
144,000 O
lbs O
. O
cheese O
( O
probably O
an O
inferior O
article O
) O
. O
550 O
ankers O
of O
Geneva B-MSC
. O
10,800 O
barrels O
of O
beer O
. O
Most O
statistical O
tables O
are O
parchingly O
dry O
in O
the O
reading O
; O
not O
so O
in O
the O
present O
case O
, O
however O
, O
where O
the O
reader O
is O
flooded O
with O
whole O
pipes O
, O
barrels O
, O
quarts O
, O
and O
gills O
of O
good O
gin O
and O
good O
cheer O
. O
At O
the O
time O
, O
I O
devoted O
three O
days O
to O
the O
studious O
digesting O
of O
all O
this O
beer O
, O
beef O
, O
and O
bread O
, O
during O
which O
many O
profound O
thoughts O
were O
incidentally O
suggested O
to O
me O
, O
capable O
of O
a O
transcendental O
and O
Platonic O
application O
; O
and O
, O
furthermore O
, O
I O
compiled O
supplementary O
tables O
of O
my O
own O
, O
touching O
the O
probable O
quantity O
of O
stock-fish O
, O
etc. O
, O
consumed O
by O
every O
Low B-GRP
Dutch I-GRP
harpooneer O
in O
that O
ancient O
Greenland B-LOC
and O
Spitzbergen B-LOC
whale O
fishery O
. O
In O
the O
first O
place O
, O
the O
amount O
of O
butter O
, O
and O
Texel B-ORG
and I-ORG
Leyden I-ORG
cheese O
consumed O
, O
seems O
amazing O
. O
I O
impute O
it O
, O
though O
, O
to O
their O
naturally O
unctuous O
natures O
, O
being O
rendered O
still O
more O
unctuous O
by O
the O
nature O
of O
their O
vocation O
, O
and O
especially O
by O
their O
pursuing O
their O
game O
in O
those O
frigid O
Polar B-LOC
Seas I-LOC
, O
on O
the O
very O
coasts O
of O
that O
Esquimaux B-GRP
country O
where O
the O
convivial O
natives O
pledge O
each O
other O
in O
bumpers O
of O
train O
oil O
. O
The O
quantity O
of O
beer O
, O
too O
, O
is O
very O
large O
, O
10,800 O
barrels O
. O
Now O
, O
as O
those O
polar O
fisheries O
could O
only O
be O
prosecuted O
in O
the O
short O
summer O
of O
that O
climate O
, O
so O
that O
the O
whole O
cruise O
of O
one O
of O
these O
Dutch B-GRP
whalemen O
, O
including O
the O
short O
voyage O
to O
and O
from O
the O
Spitzbergen B-LOC
sea O
, O
did O
not O
much O
exceed O
three O
months O
, O
say O
, O
and O
reckoning O
30 O
men O
to O
each O
of O
their O
fleet O
of O
180 O
sail O
, O
we O
have O
5,400 O
Low B-GRP
Dutch I-GRP
seamen O
in O
all O
; O
therefore O
, O
I O
say O
, O
we O
have O
precisely O
two O
barrels O
of O
beer O
per O
man O
, O
for O
a O
twelve O
weeks O
’ O
allowance O
, O
exclusive O
of O
his O
fair O
proportion O
of O
that O
550 O
ankers O
of O
gin O
. O
Now O
, O
whether O
these O
gin O
and O
beer O
harpooneers O
, O
so O
fuddled O
as O
one O
might O
fancy O
them O
to O
have O
been O
, O
were O
the O
right O
sort O
of O
men O
to O
stand O
up O
in O
a O
boat O
’ O
s O
head O
, O
and O
take O
good O
aim O
at O
flying O
whales O
; O
this O
would O
seem O
somewhat O
improbable O
. O
Yet O
they O
did O
aim O
at O
them O
, O
and O
hit O
them O
too O
. O
But O
this O
was O
very O
far O
North O
, O
be O
it O
remembered O
, O
where O
beer O
agrees O
well O
with O
the O
constitution O
; O
upon O
the O
Equator B-LOC
, O
in O
our O
southern O
fishery O
, O
beer O
would O
be O
apt O
to O
make O
the O
harpooneer O
sleepy O
at O
the O
mast-head O
and O
boozy O
in O
his O
boat O
; O
and O
grievous O
loss O
might O
ensue O
to O
Nantucket B-LOC
and O
New B-LOC
Bedford I-LOC
. O
But O
no O
more O
; O
enough O
has O
been O
said O
to O
show O
that O
the O
old O
Dutch B-GRP
whalers O
of O
two O
or O
three O
centuries O
ago O
were O
high O
livers O
; O
and O
that O
the O
English B-GRP
whalers O
have O
not O
neglected O
so O
excellent O
an O
example O
. O
For O
, O
say O
they O
, O
when O
cruising O
in O
an O
empty O
ship O
, O
if O
you O
can O
get O
nothing O
better O
out O
of O
the O
world O
, O
get O
a O
good O
dinner O
out O
of O
it O
, O
at O
least O
. O
And O
this O
empties O
the O
decanter O
. O
