# title: Moby Dick
# chapter: 14
# annotator: Vincent Labatut
# guidelines-version: 1.0.0
# last-updated: 23-05-2024
# comment: 

Nothing O
more O
happened O
on O
the O
passage O
worthy O
the O
mentioning O
; O
so O
, O
after O
a O
fine O
run O
, O
we O
safely O
arrived O
in O
Nantucket B-LOC
. O
Nantucket B-LOC
! O
Take O
out O
your O
map O
and O
look O
at O
it O
. O
See O
what O
a O
real O
corner O
of O
the O
world O
it O
occupies O
; O
how O
it O
stands O
there O
, O
away O
off O
shore O
, O
more O
lonely O
than O
the O
Eddystone B-LOC
lighthouse I-LOC
. O
Look O
at O
it—a O
mere O
hillock O
, O
and O
elbow O
of O
sand O
; O
all O
beach O
, O
without O
a O
background O
. O
There O
is O
more O
sand O
there O
than O
you O
would O
use O
in O
twenty O
years O
as O
a O
substitute O
for O
blotting O
paper O
. O
Some O
gamesome O
wights O
will O
tell O
you O
that O
they O
have O
to O
plant O
weeds O
there O
, O
they O
don O
’ O
t O
grow O
naturally O
; O
that O
they O
import O
Canada B-LOC
thistles O
; O
that O
they O
have O
to O
send O
beyond O
seas O
for O
a O
spile O
to O
stop O
a O
leak O
in O
an O
oil O
cask O
; O
that O
pieces O
of O
wood O
in O
Nantucket B-LOC
are O
carried O
about O
like O
bits O
of O
the O
true O
cross O
in O
Rome B-LOC
; O
that O
people O
there O
plant O
toadstools O
before O
their O
houses O
, O
to O
get O
under O
the O
shade O
in O
summer O
time O
; O
that O
one O
blade O
of O
grass O
makes O
an O
oasis O
, O
three O
blades O
in O
a O
day O
’ O
s O
walk O
a O
prairie O
; O
that O
they O
wear O
quicksand O
shoes O
, O
something O
like O
Laplander B-GRP
snow-shoes O
; O
that O
they O
are O
so O
shut O
up O
, O
belted O
about O
, O
every O
way O
inclosed O
, O
surrounded O
, O
and O
made O
an O
utter O
island O
of O
by O
the O
ocean O
, O
that O
to O
their O
very O
chairs O
and O
tables O
small O
clams O
will O
sometimes O
be O
found O
adhering O
, O
as O
to O
the O
backs O
of O
sea O
turtles O
. O
But O
these O
extravaganzas O
only O
show O
that O
Nantucket B-LOC
is O
no O
Illinois B-LOC
. O
Look O
now O
at O
the O
wondrous O
traditional O
story O
of O
how O
this O
island O
was O
settled O
by O
the O
red-men O
. O
Thus O
goes O
the O
legend O
. O
In O
olden O
times O
an O
eagle O
swooped O
down O
upon O
the O
New B-LOC
England I-LOC
coast O
, O
and O
carried O
off O
an O
infant O
Indian B-GRP
in O
his O
talons O
. O
With O
loud O
lament O
the O
parents O
saw O
their O
child O
borne O
out O
of O
sight O
over O
the O
wide O
waters O
. O
They O
resolved O
to O
follow O
in O
the O
same O
direction O
. O
Setting O
out O
in O
their O
canoes O
, O
after O
a O
perilous O
passage O
they O
discovered O
the O
island O
, O
and O
there O
they O
found O
an O
empty O
ivory O
casket O
, O
—the O
poor O
little O
Indian B-GRP
’ O
s O
skeleton O
. O
What O
wonder O
, O
then O
, O
that O
these O
Nantucketers B-GRP
, O
born O
on O
a O
beach O
, O
should O
take O
to O
the O
sea O
for O
a O
livelihood O
! O
They O
first O
caught O
crabs O
and O
quohogs O
in O
the O
sand O
; O
grown O
bolder O
, O
they O
waded O
out O
with O
nets O
for O
mackerel O
; O
more O
experienced O
, O
they O
pushed O
off O
in O
boats O
and O
captured O
cod O
; O
and O
at O
last O
, O
launching O
a O
navy O
of O
great O
ships O
on O
the O
sea O
, O
explored O
this O
watery O
world O
; O
put O
an O
incessant O
belt O
of O
circumnavigations O
round O
it O
; O
peeped O
in O
at O
Behring B-LOC
’ I-LOC
s I-LOC
Straits I-LOC
; O
and O
in O
all O
seasons O
and O
all O
oceans O
declared O
everlasting O
war O
with O
the O
mightiest O
animated O
mass O
that O
has O
survived O
the O
flood O
; O
most O
monstrous O
and O
most O
mountainous O
! O
That O
Himmalehan B-LOC
, O
salt-sea O
Mastodon O
, O
clothed O
with O
such O
portentousness O
of O
unconscious O
power O
, O
that O
his O
very O
panics O
are O
more O
to O
be O
dreaded O
than O
his O
most O
fearless O
and O
malicious O
assaults O
! O
And O
thus O
have O
these O
naked O
Nantucketers O
, O
these O
sea O
hermits O
, O
issuing O
from O
their O
ant-hill O
in O
the O
sea O
, O
overrun O
and O
conquered O
the O
watery O
world O
like O
so O
many O
Alexanders B-CHR
; O
parcelling O
out O
among O
them O
the O
Atlantic B-LOC
, O
Pacific B-LOC
, O
and O
Indian B-LOC
oceans I-LOC
, O
as O
the O
three O
pirate O
powers O
did O
Poland B-LOC
. O
Let O
America B-LOC
add O
Mexico B-LOC
to O
Texas B-LOC
, O
and O
pile O
Cuba B-LOC
upon O
Canada B-LOC
; O
let O
the O
English B-GRP
overswarm O
all O
India B-LOC
, O
and O
hang O
out O
their O
blazing O
banner O
from O
the O
sun O
; O
two O
thirds O
of O
this O
terraqueous O
globe O
are O
the O
Nantucketer B-GRP
’ O
s O
. O
For O
the O
sea O
is O
his O
; O
he O
owns O
it O
, O
as O
Emperors O
own O
empires O
; O
other O
seamen O
having O
but O
a O
right O
of O
way O
through O
it O
. O
Merchant O
ships O
are O
but O
extension O
bridges O
; O
armed O
ones O
but O
floating O
forts O
; O
even O
pirates O
and O
privateers O
, O
though O
following O
the O
sea O
as O
highwaymen O
the O
road O
, O
they O
but O
plunder O
other O
ships O
, O
other O
fragments O
of O
the O
land O
like O
themselves O
, O
without O
seeking O
to O
draw O
their O
living O
from O
the O
bottomless O
deep O
itself O
. O
The O
Nantucketer B-GRP
, O
he O
alone O
resides O
and O
riots O
on O
the O
sea O
; O
he O
alone O
, O
in O
Bible B-MSC
language O
, O
goes O
down O
to O
it O
in O
ships O
; O
to O
and O
fro O
ploughing O
it O
as O
his O
own O
special O
plantation O
. O
_There_ O
is O
his O
home O
; O
_there_ O
lies O
his O
business O
, O
which O
a O
Noah B-CHR
’ O
s O
flood O
would O
not O
interrupt O
, O
though O
it O
overwhelmed O
all O
the O
millions O
in O
China B-LOC
. O
He O
lives O
on O
the O
sea O
, O
as O
prairie O
cocks O
in O
the O
prairie O
; O
he O
hides O
among O
the O
waves O
, O
he O
climbs O
them O
as O
chamois O
hunters O
climb O
the O
Alps B-LOC
. O
For O
years O
he O
knows O
not O
the O
land O
; O
so O
that O
when O
he O
comes O
to O
it O
at O
last O
, O
it O
smells O
like O
another O
world O
, O
more O
strangely O
than O
the O
moon O
would O
to O
an O
Earthsman B-GRP
. O
With O
the O
landless O
gull O
, O
that O
at O
sunset O
folds O
her O
wings O
and O
is O
rocked O
to O
sleep O
between O
billows O
; O
so O
at O
nightfall O
, O
the O
Nantucketer B-GRP
, O
out O
of O
sight O
of O
land O
, O
furls O
his O
sails O
, O
and O
lays O
him O
to O
his O
rest O
, O
while O
under O
his O
very O
pillow O
rush O
herds O
of O
walruses O
and O
whales O
. O
