# title: Moby Dick
# chapter: 83
# annotator: Vincent Labatut
# guidelines-version: 1.0.0
# last-updated: 11-07-2024
# comment: 

Reference O
was O
made O
to O
the O
historical O
story O
of O
Jonah B-CHR
and O
the O
whale O
in O
the O
preceding O
chapter O
. O
Now O
some O
Nantucketers B-GRP
rather O
distrust O
this O
historical O
story O
of O
Jonah B-CHR
and O
the O
whale O
. O
But O
then O
there O
were O
some O
sceptical O
Greeks B-GRP
and O
Romans B-GRP
, O
who O
, O
standing O
out O
from O
the O
orthodox O
pagans O
of O
their O
times O
, O
equally O
doubted O
the O
story O
of O
Hercules B-CHR
and O
the O
whale O
, O
and O
Arion B-CHR
and O
the O
dolphin O
; O
and O
yet O
their O
doubting O
those O
traditions O
did O
not O
make O
those O
traditions O
one O
whit O
the O
less O
facts O
, O
for O
all O
that O
. O
One O
old O
Sag-Harbor B-LOC
whaleman O
’ O
s O
chief O
reason O
for O
questioning O
the O
Hebrew O
story O
was O
this O
: O
—He O
had O
one O
of O
those O
quaint O
old-fashioned O
Bibles B-MSC
, O
embellished O
with O
curious O
, O
unscientific O
plates O
; O
one O
of O
which O
represented O
Jonah B-CHR
’ O
s O
whale O
with O
two O
spouts O
in O
his O
head—a O
peculiarity O
only O
true O
with O
respect O
to O
a O
species O
of O
the O
Leviathan B-CHR
( O
the O
Right O
Whale O
, O
and O
the O
varieties O
of O
that O
order O
) O
, O
concerning O
which O
the O
fishermen O
have O
this O
saying O
, O
“ O
A O
penny O
roll O
would O
choke O
him O
” O
; O
his O
swallow O
is O
so O
very O
small O
. O
But O
, O
to O
this O
, O
Bishop B-CHR
Jebb I-CHR
’ O
s O
anticipative O
answer O
is O
ready O
. O
It O
is O
not O
necessary O
, O
hints O
the O
Bishop O
, O
that O
we O
consider O
Jonah B-CHR
as O
tombed O
in O
the O
whale O
’ O
s O
belly O
, O
but O
as O
temporarily O
lodged O
in O
some O
part O
of O
his O
mouth O
. O
And O
this O
seems O
reasonable O
enough O
in O
the O
good O
Bishop O
. O
For O
truly O
, O
the O
Right O
Whale O
’ O
s O
mouth O
would O
accommodate O
a O
couple O
of O
whist-tables O
, O
and O
comfortably O
seat O
all O
the O
players O
. O
Possibly O
, O
too O
, O
Jonah B-CHR
might O
have O
ensconced O
himself O
in O
a O
hollow O
tooth O
; O
but O
, O
on O
second O
thoughts O
, O
the O
Right O
Whale O
is O
toothless O
. O
Another O
reason O
which O
Sag-Harbor B-CHR
( O
he O
went O
by O
that O
name O
) O
urged O
for O
his O
want O
of O
faith O
in O
this O
matter O
of O
the O
prophet O
, O
was O
something O
obscurely O
in O
reference O
to O
his O
incarcerated O
body O
and O
the O
whale O
’ O
s O
gastric O
juices O
. O
But O
this O
objection O
likewise O
falls O
to O
the O
ground O
, O
because O
a O
German B-GRP
exegetist O
supposes O
that O
Jonah B-CHR
must O
have O
taken O
refuge O
in O
the O
floating O
body O
of O
a O
_dead_ O
whale—even O
as O
the O
French B-GRP
soldiers O
in O
the O
Russian B-GRP
campaign O
turned O
their O
dead O
horses O
into O
tents O
, O
and O
crawled O
into O
them O
. O
Besides O
, O
it O
has O
been O
divined O
by O
other O
continental O
commentators O
, O
that O
when O
Jonah B-CHR
was O
thrown O
overboard O
from O
the O
Joppa B-LOC
ship O
, O
he O
straightway O
effected O
his O
escape O
to O
another O
vessel O
near O
by O
, O
some O
vessel O
with O
a O
whale O
for O
a O
figure-head O
; O
and O
, O
I O
would O
add O
, O
possibly O
called O
“ O
The O
Whale O
, O
” O
as O
some O
craft O
are O
nowadays O
christened O
the O
“ O
Shark O
, O
” O
the O
“ O
Gull O
, O
” O
the O
“ O
Eagle. O
” O
Nor O
have O
there O
been O
wanting O
learned O
exegetists O
who O
have O
opined O
that O
the O
whale O
mentioned O
in O
the O
book O
of O
Jonah B-CHR
merely O
meant O
a O
life-preserver—an O
inflated O
bag O
of O
wind—which O
the O
endangered O
prophet O
swam O
to O
, O
and O
so O
was O
saved O
from O
a O
watery O
doom O
. O
Poor O
Sag-Harbor B-CHR
, O
therefore O
, O
seems O
worsted O
all O
round O
. O
But O
he O
had O
still O
another O
reason O
for O
his O
want O
of O
faith O
. O
It O
was O
this O
, O
if O
I O
remember O
right O
: O
Jonah B-CHR
was O
swallowed O
by O
the O
whale O
in O
the O
Mediterranean B-LOC
Sea I-LOC
, O
and O
after O
three O
days O
he O
was O
vomited O
up O
somewhere O
within O
three O
days O
’ O
journey O
of O
Nineveh B-LOC
, O
a O
city O
on O
the O
Tigris B-LOC
, O
very O
much O
more O
than O
three O
days O
’ O
journey O
across O
from O
the O
nearest O
point O
of O
the O
Mediterranean B-LOC
coast I-LOC
. O
How O
is O
that O
? O
But O
was O
there O
no O
other O
way O
for O
the O
whale O
to O
land O
the O
prophet O
within O
that O
short O
distance O
of O
Nineveh B-LOC
? O
Yes O
. O
He O
might O
have O
carried O
him O
round O
by O
the O
way O
of O
the O
Cape B-LOC
of I-LOC
Good I-LOC
Hope I-LOC
. O
But O
not O
to O
speak O
of O
the O
passage O
through O
the O
whole O
length O
of O
the O
Mediterranean B-LOC
, O
and O
another O
passage O
up O
the O
Persian B-LOC
Gulf I-LOC
and O
Red B-LOC
Sea I-LOC
, O
such O
a O
supposition O
would O
involve O
the O
complete O
circumnavigation O
of O
all O
Africa B-LOC
in O
three O
days O
, O
not O
to O
speak O
of O
the O
Tigris B-LOC
waters O
, O
near O
the O
site O
of O
Nineveh B-LOC
, O
being O
too O
shallow O
for O
any O
whale O
to O
swim O
in O
. O
Besides O
, O
this O
idea O
of O
Jonah B-CHR
’ O
s O
weathering O
the O
Cape B-LOC
of I-LOC
Good I-LOC
Hope I-LOC
at O
so O
early O
a O
day O
would O
wrest O
the O
honor O
of O
the O
discovery O
of O
that O
great O
headland O
from O
Bartholomew B-CHR
Diaz I-CHR
, O
its O
reputed O
discoverer O
, O
and O
so O
make O
modern O
history O
a O
liar O
. O
But O
all O
these O
foolish O
arguments O
of O
old O
Sag-Harbor B-CHR
only O
evinced O
his O
foolish O
pride O
of O
reason—a O
thing O
still O
more O
reprehensible O
in O
him O
, O
seeing O
that O
he O
had O
but O
little O
learning O
except O
what O
he O
had O
picked O
up O
from O
the O
sun O
and O
the O
sea O
. O
I O
say O
it O
only O
shows O
his O
foolish O
, O
impious O
pride O
, O
and O
abominable O
, O
devilish O
rebellion O
against O
the O
reverend O
clergy O
. O
For O
by O
a O
Portuguese B-GRP
Catholic B-ORG
priest O
, O
this O
very O
idea O
of O
Jonah B-CHR
’ O
s O
going O
to O
Nineveh B-LOC
via O
the O
Cape B-LOC
of I-LOC
Good I-LOC
Hope I-LOC
was O
advanced O
as O
a O
signal O
magnification O
of O
the O
general O
miracle O
. O
And O
so O
it O
was O
. O
Besides O
, O
to O
this O
day O
, O
the O
highly O
enlightened O
Turks B-GRP
devoutly O
believe O
in O
the O
historical O
story O
of O
Jonah B-CHR
. O
And O
some O
three O
centuries O
ago O
, O
an O
English B-GRP
traveller O
in O
old O
Harris B-CHR
’ O
s O
Voyages O
, O
speaks O
of O
a O
Turkish B-GRP
Mosque O
built O
in O
honor O
of O
Jonah B-CHR
, O
in O
which O
Mosque O
was O
a O
miraculous O
lamp O
that O
burnt O
without O
any O
oil O
. O
